Guide to the Mark Busby Accessions
The Wittliff Collections
Mark Busby Accessions
1976-2011
The Wittliff Collections https://www.thewittliffcollections.txstate.edu
Busby, Mark
UPWC.16145
2 Linear Feet
2 boxes
Multiple accessions from scholar and author, Mark Busby document his research and writing. His archive also includes substantial records from the Texas Institute of Letters, for which Busby is past President.
Conditions Governing Access
Collection is open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gifts of Mark Busby, 1991-2021
Biographical Note
A scholar noted for his writing on the literature of the American West, Mark Busby the author and editor of several books, as well as a novelist (Fort Benning Blues and Cedar Crossing) and the co-editor of the journals Southwestern American Literature and Texas Books in Review. Busby is a professor of English at Texas State University, where he directs the Center for the Study of the Southwest and the Southwest Regional Humanities Center. Busby is also a past president of the Texas Institute of Letters.
Busby's books include John Graves, Writer (co-editor, 2007), The Southwest: The Greenwood Encyclopedia of American Regional Cultures (editor, 2004), From Texas to the World and Back: Essays on the Journeys of Katherine Anne Porter (co-editor, 2001), Fort Benning Blues: A Novel (2001), Larry McMurtry and the West: An Ambivalent Relationship (1995), New Growth 2: Contemporary Short Stories by Texas Writers (editor, 1993), United States Authors Series-Ralph Ellison (1991), The Frontier Experience and the American Dream: Essays on American Literature (co-editor 1989), Lanford Wilson (Western Writers Series, 1987), Preston Jones (Western Writers Series, 1983).
Mark Busby began donating his papers to the Southwestern Writers Collection/The Wittliff Collections in 1991.
Scope and Contents
Multiple accessions from scholar and author, Mark Busby document his research and writing. His archive also includes substantial records from the Texas Institute of Letters, for which Busby is past President.
Index Terms
Subjects (Corporations)
Texas Institute of Letters
- Accession 2016-145
  Abstract
  Archival materials received from Mark Busby, 2002-2004 President of The Texas Institute of Letters, majority of the materials pertaining to TIL from 1976-2011. Included in the collection are membership nominations, TIL Award information, newsletters, and directories. The folder titles preceding a semicolon reflect Busby's original descriptions.
  - Three The Texas Institute of Letters Awards Banquet programs, including lists of awards and correspondence, 1998-2011 (Box 2492, Folder 1)
  - Manuscript drafts by Brennan Vaverek such as "The Survival of the Cowboy" "The Last Cowboy", and "The Log of a Cowboy", including correspondence between Vaverek and Busby, 1996 (Box 2492, Folder 2)
  - "Personal"; Royalty statements, book reviews, and correspondence, 2000-2002 (Box 2492, Folder 3)
  - "TIL Council Minutes"; Texas Institute of Letters Council meeting minutes, 1992-1999 (Box 2492, Folder 4)
  - "Paisano Challenge Grant Fund"; Pledges for the Paisano Challenge Grant Fund, 1998-2000 (Box 2492, Folder 5)
  - "Angelo State 2001"; Call for papers at Angelo State University, 2000-2001 (Box 2492, Folder 6)
  - "Tex. Inst. of Letters"; TIL Newsletters, 1992-1999 (Box 2492, Folder 7)
  - Articles such as "A Cracker's Farewell" and "Bringing It All Back Home", correspondence, and drafts, 1998-2000 (Box 2492, Folder 8)
  - "TX Book Fest 2000"; Biographies for writers, Barry Lopez and Rick Bass (Box 2492, Folder 9)
  - "Map to [Home]"; Handwritten map of the Busby house, August 6, 1996 (Box 2492, Folder 10)
  - "Book Reviews Flyer"; Michelle Pierce's paper, narrative description of proposed project, and correspondence, 1996 (Box 2492, Folder 11)
  - TIL Awards Banquet and 2011 Directory, including a note from Marion Winik, 1976-2011 (Box 2492, Folder 12)
  - Texas Book Festival folders, including flyer for the 2002 Texas Book Festival, November 14-17, 2002 (Box 2492, Folder 13)
  - 2001 Texas Book Festival folder and programs, November 15-18, 2001 (Box 2492, Folder 14)
  - Texas Journal of Ideas, History, and Culture, including two Vietnam: From A Texas POV Southwestern Writers Collection programs, 1997-2005 (Box 2492, Folder 15)
  - Texas Institute of Letters Directories, 2009-2010 (Box 2492, Folder 16)
  - The Texas Institute of Letters programs, including TIL Meeting of the Council, 2004-2010 (Box 2492, Folder 17)
  - "TIL"; Texas Institute of Letters newsletters, news releases, and correspondence, 1998-2002 (Box 2492, Folder 18)
  - "TIL"; Texas Institute of Letters membership nominations, programs, and menu for TIL events, 2000-2002 (Box 2492, Folder 19)
  - Texas Institute of Letters program and membership nominations, 2008 (Box 2492, Folder 20)
  - Texas Institute of Letters membership nominations, newsletters, and TIL Agenda, 2003-2009 (Box 2492, Folder 21)
  - Photograph of Steve Turner, correspondence, and Turner's biography, 2001 (Box 2492, Folder 22)
  - Texas Institute of Letters Council meeting agenda, by-laws, and correspondence, 1987-2003 (Box 2492, Folder 23)
  - Texas Institute of Letters membership nominations, voting ballots, correspondence, and Maryln Schwartz's membership nomination, 2000-2001 (Box 2492, Folder 24)
  - "TIL"; Texas Institute of Letters membership nominations, 2009-2010 (Box 2492, Folder 25)
  - "Banquets 2001 & 2002"; List of duties for Texas Institute of Letters President, menus for the banquets, and lists of Award winners and presenters, 1998-2002 (Box 2492, Folder 26)
  - Texas Institute of Letters certifications of membership, 2003 (Box 2492, Folder 27)
  - CD titled "TIL 2011" containing membership nominations, including two floppy disks titled "Variations on Hoggard's Schedule" and "Osborn's TIL Info & forms" (Box 2492, Folder 28)
  - Dobie Paisano Award information, applicants, and news clipping, 2004 (Box 2492, Folder 29)
  - List of Texas Institute of Letters Awards and press release, 2003-2005 (Box 2492, Folder 30)
  - Texas Institute of Letters membership nomination packets (2 folders), 2004 (Box 2493, Folder 1-2)
  - Texas Institute of Letters Awards Banquet programs, 2003-2004 (Box 2493, Folder 3)
  - Texas Institute of Letters newsletter, directory, and "The Formative Years, 1896-1923", 2002-2010 (Box 2493, Folder 4)
  - Membership nominations, including short story entries "If Nights Could Talk", "The La Salle Expedition to Texas", and "A Dawn Attack", 2001 (Box 2493, Folder 5)
  - Texas Institute of Letters membership nominations, in alphabetical order, B-E, 2006 (Box 2493, Folder 6)
  - Texas Institute of Letters membership nominations, in alphabetical order, G-M, 2006 (Box 2493, Folder 7)
  - Texas Institute of Letters membership nominations, in alphabetical order, R-W, 2006 (Box 2493, Folder 8)
  - Texas Institute of Letters newsletters, directories, and programs for Award Banquets, 1997-2007 (Box 2493, Folder 9)
  - Texas Institute of Letters membership nominations (2 folders), 2005 (Box 2493, Folder 10-11)
  - Texas Institute of Letters 64th Annual Awards Banquet programs, April 15, 2000 (Box 2493, Folder 12)
  - Texas Institute of Letters membership nominations, including January 21, 2006, council meeting agenda, 2001-2006 (Box 2493, Folder 13)